<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
 * See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional
 * information regarding copyright ownership.
 *
 * This is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 * under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
 * published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
 * the License, or (at your option) any later version.
 *
 * This software is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
 * but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 * MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 * Lesser General Public License for more details.
 *
 * You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
 * License along with this software; if not, write to the Free
 * Software Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
 * 02110-1301 USA, or see the FSF site: http://www.fsf.org.
-->

<xwikidoc version="1.6" reference="SOPManager.WebHome" locale="">
  <web>SOPManager</web>
  <name>WebHome</name>
  <language/>
  <defaultLanguage/>
  <translation>0</translation>
  <creator>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</creator>
  <parent>Main.WebHome</parent>
  <author>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</author>
  <contentAuthor>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</contentAuthor>
  <version>1.1</version>
  <title>SOP Manager</title>
  <comment/>
  <minorEdit>false</minorEdit>
  <syntaxId>xwiki/2.1</syntaxId>
  <hidden>false</hidden>
  <content>{{velocity}}
{{liveData
  id="sopManagerTable"
  properties="doc.title,status,reviewerGroups,approverGroups,releaseDate,revisionPlannedDate,pDFSecondaryTargetLocation"
  source="liveTable"
  sourceParameters="className=SOPManager.Code.ControlledDocumentClass&amp;translationPrefix=platform.index.&amp;queryFilters=currentlanguage"
}}
{{/velocity}}

{{toc/}}

= SOP Manager =

SOP Manager helps teams control important procedures, policies, work instructions, and other official documents. It provides a clear review and approval workflow, keeps responsibilities visible, generates approved PDF versions, and archives the final files in File Manager.

This page gives a practical overview for business users, reviewers, approvers, and document owners.

== What SOP Manager is used for ==

Use SOP Manager when a document must follow a controlled lifecycle before it becomes official. Typical examples include:

* Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs)
* Policies and internal rules
* Work instructions
* Quality or compliance documents
* Forms, templates, and controlled records

The application is designed to answer three simple questions:

* Which documents are currently being prepared, reviewed, or approved?
* Who is responsible for the next step?
* Where is the approved PDF version stored?

== Main Dashboard ==

The table at the top of this page lists controlled documents and their main workflow information.

Use it to quickly check:

* the document title
* the current workflow status
* the reviewer and approver groups
* the release date and planned revision date
* the archived PDF location in File Manager, when available

This dashboard is intended as a central overview. The actual workflow actions are performed from each controlled document, using the SOP Manager tab.

== User Roles ==

SOP Manager works with three practical responsibilities.

; Document owner
: Prepares the document, updates the content, submits it for review, and starts new revisions when needed.

; Reviewer
: Checks whether the content is correct, complete, and ready to move forward. A reviewer can submit the document for approval or return it for changes.

; Approver
: Performs the final validation. An approver can approve the document or return it for changes.

The same person may have more than one responsibility, depending on how the workflow is configured for a document.

== Workflow Statuses ==

Each controlled document has one workflow status.

; Draft
: The document is being prepared or updated. The document owner can edit the content and workflow information.

; Submitted for Review
: The document is waiting for reviewers. Reviewers are expected to check the content and decide whether it can move to approval.

; Submitted for Approval
: The document has passed review and is waiting for final approval.

; Approved
: The document has been approved. During approval, the official PDF is generated, attached to the source page, and archived in File Manager.

; Returned for Changes
: The document was sent back because updates are required before it can continue.

== Typical Workflow ==

A common document lifecycle looks like this:

1. A user adds a page to the SOP workflow.
1. The document starts as **Draft**.
1. The document owner prepares the content and metadata.
1. The document owner submits the document for review.
1. Reviewers check the document.
1. Reviewers either submit it for approval or return it for changes.
1. Approvers perform the final check.
1. The document is approved, the PDF is generated, and the approved PDF is archived.
1. A new revision can later be started when the document needs to be updated again.

== Adding a Document to the Workflow ==

To manage a page as a controlled document, use the page action that adds the document to the SOP workflow.

After the page is added, the SOP Manager tab becomes the main place where users can see the workflow information and perform the available actions.

== SOP Manager Tab ==

The SOP Manager tab is available on controlled documents. It shows the workflow information and the actions available to the current user.

Depending on the document status and your responsibility, you may see actions such as:

* Submit for Review
* Return for Changes
* Submit for Approval
* Approve
* Start New Revision

The tab also shows the relevant workflow metadata, such as reviewers, approvers, revision information, planned revision date, and PDF template selection.

== Review Step ==

When a document is submitted for review, the reviewer group is responsible for checking it.

Reviewers should verify that:

* the content is correct and complete
* the document follows the expected structure
* required information is filled in
* the document is ready for final approval

If the document is ready, reviewers submit it for approval. If changes are needed, reviewers return it for changes.

== Approval Step ==

When a document is submitted for approval, the approver group is responsible for the final decision.

Before approval, the approver should check that:

* the document has been reviewed
* the planned revision date is valid and in the future
* the selected PDF template is correct
* the document is ready to become the official controlled version

When the document is approved, SOP Manager generates the PDF and stores the official file.

== PDF Generation and Templates ==

During approval, SOP Manager generates a PDF version of the controlled document.

The user can choose the PDF template before generating the file. The available templates include:

* portrait template for regular documents
* landscape template for wide tables or forms

For wide documents, the landscape template is intended to provide a better PDF result.

The generated PDF is attached to the original document. This allows users to keep the approved PDF directly on the source page.

== File Manager Archive ==

After approval, the generated PDF is also archived in File Manager.

The File Manager archive is useful because it provides a centralized place for approved files. The archived file keeps a link back to the original SOP page, so users can move from the official PDF to the source controlled document when needed.

The archived File Manager entry can also expose SOP-related tags, making it easier to organize and find approved files.

== User Profile Queues ==

SOP Manager adds workflow queues to user profiles so each user can see the documents that require attention.

The available queues include:

* documents owned by the current user
* documents waiting for review
* documents waiting for approval

These queues help users focus on the documents where they have an active responsibility.

== Notifications ==

SOP Manager sends internal notifications when workflow actions are performed. These notifications help users understand when a document has moved to a new step and when their attention may be required.

Typical notification moments include:

* a document is submitted for review
* a document is returned for changes
* a document is submitted for approval
* a document is approved

== Starting a New Revision ==

After a document has been approved, a new revision can be started when the content needs to be updated again.

Starting a new revision moves the document back into a working state so the next version can be prepared, reviewed, approved, and archived again.

== Practical Recommendations ==

For a clean workflow, users should follow these practices:

* keep the document content complete before submitting it for review
* choose reviewer and approver groups carefully
* use the planned revision date to indicate when the next review or update is expected
* select the PDF template that best matches the document layout
* use File Manager as the reference location for approved PDF versions
* use profile queues to track documents waiting for your action

== Summary ==

SOP Manager provides a controlled document process inside XWiki. It helps teams prepare documents, route them through review and approval, generate official PDFs, and archive approved versions in File Manager.

For daily use, start from the dashboard to identify documents, open the controlled page, and use the SOP Manager tab to perform the next workflow action.
</content>
  <object>
    <name>SOPManager.WebHome</name>
    <number>0</number>
    <className>XWiki.UIExtensionClass</className>
    <guid>21eb86e9-b139-4ad6-909c-f39b9b96e15c</guid>
    <class>
      <name>XWiki.UIExtensionClass</name>
      <customClass/>
      <customMapping/>
      <defaultViewSheet/>
      <defaultEditSheet/>
      <defaultWeb/>
      <nameField/>
      <validationScript/>
      <async_cached>
        <defaultValue>0</defaultValue>
        <disabled>0</disabled>
        <displayFormType>select</displayFormType>
        <displayType/>
        <name>async_cached</name>
        <number>3</number>
        <prettyName>Cached</prettyName>
        <unmodifiable>0</unmodifiable>
        <classType>com.xpn.xwiki.objects.classes.BooleanClass</classType>
      </async_cached>
      <async_context>
        <cache>0</cache>
        <disabled>0</disabled>
        <displayType>select</displayType>
        <freeText>forbidden</freeText>
        <largeStorage>0</largeStorage>
        <multiSelect>1</multiSelect>
        <name>async_context</name>
        <number>4</number>
        <prettyName>Context elements</prettyName>
        <relationalStorage>0</relationalStorage>
        <separator>, </separator>
        <separators>|, </separators>
        <size>5</size>
        <unmodifiable>0</unmodifiable>
        <values>action=Action|doc.reference=Document|doc.revision|icon.theme=Icon theme|locale=Language|rendering.defaultsyntax=Default syntax|rendering.restricted=Restricted|rendering.targetsyntax=Target syntax|request.base=Request base URL|request.cookies|request.headers|request.parameters=Request parameters|request.remoteAddr|request.session|request.url=Request URL|request.wiki=Request wiki|sheet|user=User|wiki=Wiki</values>
        <classType>com.xpn.xwiki.objects.classes.StaticListClass</classType>
      </async_context>
      <async_enabled>
        <defaultValue>0</defaultValue>
        <disabled>0</disabled>
        <displayFormType>select</displayFormType>
        <displayType/>
        <name>async_enabled</name>
        <number>2</number>
        <prettyName>Asynchronous rendering</prettyName>
        <unmodifiable>0</unmodifiable>
        <classType>com.xpn.xwiki.objects.classes.BooleanClass</classType>
      </async_enabled>
      <content>
        <disabled>0</disabled>
        <editor>Text</editor>
        <name>content</name>
        <number>1</number>
        <prettyName>Executed Content</prettyName>
        <restricted>0</restricted>
        <rows>25</rows>
        <size>120</size>
        <unmodifiable>0</unmodifiable>
        <classType>com.xpn.xwiki.objects.classes.TextAreaClass</classType>
      </content>
      <extensionPointId>
        <disabled>0</disabled>
        <name>extensionPointId</name>
        <number>5</number>
        <prettyName>Extension Point ID</prettyName>
        <size>30</size>
        <unmodifiable>0</unmodifiable>
        <classType>com.xpn.xwiki.objects.classes.StringClass</classType>
      </extensionPointId>
      <name>
        <disabled>0</disabled>
        <name>name</name>
        <number>6</number>
        <prettyName>Extension ID</prettyName>
        <size>30</size>
        <unmodifiable>0</unmodifiable>
        <classType>com.xpn.xwiki.objects.classes.StringClass</classType>
      </name>
      <parameters>
        <contenttype>PureText</contenttype>
        <disabled>0</disabled>
        <editor>PureText</editor>
        <name>parameters</name>
        <number>7</number>
        <prettyName>Extension Parameters</prettyName>
        <restricted>0</restricted>
        <rows>10</rows>
        <size>40</size>
        <unmodifiable>0</unmodifiable>
        <classType>com.xpn.xwiki.objects.classes.TextAreaClass</classType>
      </parameters>
      <scope>
        <cache>0</cache>
        <disabled>0</disabled>
        <displayType>select</displayType>
        <freeText>forbidden</freeText>
        <largeStorage>0</largeStorage>
        <multiSelect>0</multiSelect>
        <name>scope</name>
        <number>8</number>
        <prettyName>Extension Scope</prettyName>
        <relationalStorage>0</relationalStorage>
        <separator> </separator>
        <separators>|, </separators>
        <size>1</size>
        <unmodifiable>0</unmodifiable>
        <values>wiki=Current Wiki|user=Current User|global=Global</values>
        <classType>com.xpn.xwiki.objects.classes.StaticListClass</classType>
      </scope>
    </class>
    <property>
      <async_cached>0</async_cached>
    </property>
    <property>
      <async_context/>
    </property>
    <property>
      <async_enabled>0</async_enabled>
    </property>
    <property>
      <content/>
    </property>
    <property>
      <extensionPointId>org.xwiki.platform.panels.Applications</extensionPointId>
    </property>
    <property>
      <name>org.xwiki.contrib.applications.SOPManager</name>
    </property>
    <property>
      <parameters>label=$services.localization.render('sopManager.name')
target=SOPManager.WebHome
icon=icon:refresh</parameters>
    </property>
    <property>
      <scope/>
    </property>
  </object>
</xwikidoc>
